<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>jkit on Dave's Homepage</title><link>https://whileydave.com/tags/jkit/</link><description>Recent content in jkit on Dave's Homepage</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-nz</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2013 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://whileydave.com/tags/jkit/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>OwnKit: Inferring Modularly Checkable Ownership Annotations for Java</title><link>https://whileydave.com/publications/dpp13_aswec/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://whileydave.com/publications/dpp13_aswec/</guid><description>Abstract: Ownership and related systems impose restrictions on the object graph that can help improve program structure, exploit concurrency and verify software. Such systems rely on the presence of appropriate ownership annotations in the source code.</description></item><item><title>Formalisation and Implementation of an Algorithm for Bytecode Verification of @NonNull Types</title><link>https://whileydave.com/publications/mppd11_scp/</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://whileydave.com/publications/mppd11_scp/</guid><description>Abstract. Java&amp;rsquo;s annotation mechanism allows us to extend its type system with non-null types. Checking such types cannot be done using the existing bytecode verification algorithm. We extend this algorithm to verify non-null types using a novel technique that identifies aliasing relationships between local variables and stack locations in the JVM.</description></item><item><title>JPure: a Modular Purity System for Java</title><link>https://whileydave.com/publications/pea11_cc/</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://whileydave.com/publications/pea11_cc/</guid><description>Abstract: Purity Analysis is the problem of determining whether or not a method may have side-effects. This has applications in automatic parallelisation, extended static checking, and more. We present a novel purity system for Java that employs purity annotations which can be checked modularly.</description></item><item><title>Java Bytecode Verification for @NonNull Types</title><link>https://whileydave.com/publications/mppd08_cc/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://whileydave.com/publications/mppd08_cc/</guid><description>Abstract: Java’s annotation mechanism allows us to extend its type system with non-null types. However, checking such types cannot be done using the existing bytecode verification algorithm. We extend this algorithm to verify non-null types using a novel technique that identifies aliasing relationships between local variables and stack locations in the JVM.</description></item><item><title>The Java Compiler Kit</title><link>https://whileydave.com/projects/jkit/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://whileydave.com/projects/jkit/</guid><description>The Java Compiler Kit is a straightforward implementation of a Java compiler, designed with extensibility in mind. In building the JKit compiler, the aims were: firstly, to help with teaching compilers by considering an implementation for a fully fledged language (Java), rather than a stripped-down imitation language; secondly, to aid research in programming languages, compilers and verification.</description></item></channel></rss>