<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>gilk on Dave's Homepage</title><link>https://whileydave.com/tags/gilk/</link><description>Recent content in gilk on Dave's Homepage</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-nz</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2002 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://whileydave.com/tags/gilk/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>GILK: A Dynamic Instrumentation Tool for the Linux Kernel</title><link>https://whileydave.com/publications/pkfh02_tools/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2002 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://whileydave.com/publications/pkfh02_tools/</guid><description>Abstract: This paper desribes a dynamic instrumentation tool for the Linux Kernal which allows a stock Linux kernel to be modified while in execution, with instruments implemented as kernel modules. The Intel x86 architecture poses a particular problem, due to variable length instructions, which this paper addresses for the first time.</description></item><item><title>GILK</title><link>https://whileydave.com/projects/gilk/</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2000 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://whileydave.com/projects/gilk/</guid><description>The GILK project was part of my master&amp;rsquo;s thesis at Imperial College London. The project is all about dynamic instrumentation of the Linux Kernel. This means that a stock (i.e. without any source code modification) kernel can be instrumented whilst in execution!</description></item><item><title>Instrumenting the Linux Kernel</title><link>https://whileydave.com/publications/pearce00_meng/</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2000 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://whileydave.com/publications/pearce00_meng/</guid><description>Abstract: An instrumentation tool has been developed for the Linux kernel that uses the relatively new technique of runtime code splicing. This permits instrumentation of a running system, without any source code modification, by redirecting the flow of control to pass through carefully written code patches.</description></item></channel></rss>